A Guide to the Papers of Dr. Lewis Hinton Bosher, Jr., 1891-1994
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
- Medical College of Virginia Papers, 1949-1979 (Box 2-3)
  - Department of Surgery, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 2:42)
    Correspondence primarily from the time when Dr. Lazar J. Greenfield became head of the department after the death of Dr. David Hume.
  - Facilities - Space Issues, 1954-1967 (Box-folder 2:43)
    Correspondence with William F. Tompkins of the Space Committee and others over office space concerns.
  - Facilities - Thoracic and Cardiac Surgery facilities 1964-1969 (Box-folder 2:44)
    Correspondence, plans, and specifications related to the conversion of MCV-West, 11th Floor, East Wing to operating rooms and additional facilities for thoracic and cardiac surgery.
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes, 25 May 1962 (Box-folder 2:45)
  - Heart-Lung Project, 1959-1963 (Box-folder 2:46)
    Correspondence related to funding and progress of the project; includes a photograph of a coronary perfusion unit.
  - Infections Committee, 1959, 1970 (Box-folder 2:47)
  - Medical Curriculum and Instruction, 1950-1962 (Box-folder 2:48)
    Contains papers relating to Bosher's service on the Medical Curriculum Committee, letters regarding teaching methods, and other related items.
  - Newspaper Clippings (Box-folder 2:49)
  - Operating Rooms, 1951-1979 (Box-folder 2:50)
    Memos and other correspondence related to scheduling, equipment, and procedures.
  - Photographs (Box-folder 3:1)
    Black and white photographs of Drs. Isaac A. Bigger, Barney Brooks, and Beverly Douglas
  - Residents, 1961-1979 (Box-folder 3:2)
    Listing of residents by year and a 1976 memo outlining resident rotations.
  - Scrub Nurses, 1951-1976 (Box-folder 3:3)
    Correspondence and memos detailing the duties of nurses in thoracic and cardiac surgery.
  - Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery Correspondence, 1949-1979 (Box-folder 3:4-6)
- Subject Files, 1951-1979 (Box 3)
  - Aortograms (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Blood Volume, 1961-1965 (Box-folder 3:8)
    Relating mostly to the Volemetron computer used for determining blood volume.
  - Cardiovascular Issues, 1957-1971 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Congenital Heart Clinic, 1951-1969 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Ethylene Oxide Sterilization, 1959-1971 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Extracorporeal Circulation, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Freeze Drying for Vascular Grafts, 1953-1955 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Hollow Filament Fabric Oxygenator, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Japan and London visits, 1968, 1974 (Box-folder 3:15)
    Trips to London (1968) to visit other vascular surgeons and Japan (1974) for the 2nd Asian Congress on Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery. Includes some unidentified surgery photographs related to the trips
  - Manuscript Requests (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Medical Devices - Cardiovascular (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Medical Devices - Oxygenator (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Medical Devices and Research (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Recommendations (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Retirement Letters, 1979 (Box-folder 3:21)
    Copies of letters written by Bosher to various colleagues announcing his retirement from MVC.
  - Review Requests 1962, 1965, 1976 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Steed v. Custer, 1963 (Box-folder 3:23)
    Re: Bosher's consultation for a malpractice case.
  - Sterilization Equipment and Procedures (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Surgical Assistants (Box-folder 3:25)
  - Surgical Procedures (Box-folder 3:26)
  - Thoracic Surgical Training at 2nd Year Level 1959 (Box-folder 3:27)
    Contains the responses from the various programs about placement of a resident for a one year.
  - Ultraviolet Light (Box-folder 3:28)
- Bigger Biographical Sketch Project, 1923-1987 (Boxe 3-4)
  - A-B, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 3:29)
  - C-D, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 3:30)
  - E-G, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 3:31)
  - H-K, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 3:32)
  - L-N, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 3:33)
  - O-Q, 1983-1987 (Box-folder 3:34)
  - R-T, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 3:35)
  - U-Z, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 3:36)
  - Isaac Alexander Bigger, Jr. M.D. (1893-1955) A Biographical Sketch,1986 (Box-folder 3:37-38)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Dr. Bigger, 1940-1955 (Box-folder 3:39)
  - Orders for Appendix to sketch, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 3:40)
  - Photograph (Box-folder 3:41)
  - A Physician for All Time, undated (Box-folder 3:42)
    A lecture delivered to a group at St. Stephen's Church, Richmond, Virginia.
  - Bigger's Correspondence, 1926-1955 (Box-folder 3:43)
    Correspondence collected by Bosher from family and friends of Dr. Bigger since according to Bosher most of Bigger's papers were lost, discarded, or destroyed.
  - Bigger's Journal Articles, 1923-1954 (Box-folders 3:44-45)
    Copies or reprints of articles written by Dr. Bigger.
  - Classmates of Dr. Bigger, 1983 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Colleagues and Acquaintances of Dr. Bigger, 1946, 1971-1986 (Box-folder 4:2)
    The letter from 1946 was to Drs. Shelton Horsley and Isaac Bigger from Z.M. Ma of China. The surgeon expressed how valuable their book Operative Surgery had been for him. Bosher attempted to contact Ma while writing the sketch.
  - Former Residents of Dr. Bigger, 1981 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Other Research and Resources (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Richmond Academy of Medicine (Box-folder 4:5)
    Contains copies of resolutions written on the death of members of the Academy. The file includes resolutions written about doctors who were contemporaries of Bigger.
- Dr. Lewis C. Bosher 1891-1986 (Box 4)
  - Genito-Urinary Surgery and Venereal Disease, 1905-1910, Bound volume, 374 pages. Approximately three quarters of the volume is filled with typed notes pasted to the pages and some handwritten items. The binding is deteriorated and fragile. (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Special Fractures, 1899 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Medical College of Virginia materials, 1891-1916 (Box-folder 4:8)
    This file contains a few items related Bosher's tenure at MCV including an Annual Catalogue for the 1981-1892 session, a list of genito-urinary patients with diagnosis and treatment, September 1914 - January 1915, and an invitation to a banquet at the Jefferson Hotel given by Bosher to meet the class of 1919.
  - Miscellaneous Resources and Materials 1905-1986 (Box-folder 4:9)
    Items such as articles about Lewis C. Bosher collected by Lewis H. Bosher in anticipation of writing a historical sketch of his great uncle.
  - Printed Materials, 1905-1912 (Box-folder 4:10)
    Reprints of two journal articles and medical advertisements related to Bosher's area of medicine.
  - Resolutions on the death of Dr. Lewis C. Bosher, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Sarcoma of the Testicle, 1902 (Box-folder 4:12)
    Reprint of a journal article by Lewis C. Bosher.
- 7 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified Manuscript, circa 1913 (Box-folder 4:12-13)
    The manuscript covers the subject of angiorraphy and probably dates from around 1913.